<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The discipline and habit of virgins· Written in Latin by the holy martyr St. Cyprian, Arch-bishop of Carthage Translated into English.</title>
            <author>Cyprian, Saint, Bishop of Carthage.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81203</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895487</idno>
  <idno type="VID">152926</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240920125</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7712D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229667</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895487</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99895487e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81203)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152926)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2334:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The discipline and habit of virgins· Written in Latin by the holy martyr St. Cyprian, Arch-bishop of Carthage Translated into English.</title>
                  <author>Cyprian, Saint, Bishop of Carthage.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Virginity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Young women --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152926:1"/>
            <p>THE Discipline and Habit OF VIRGINS.</p>
            <p>Written in Latin by the HOLY MARTYR St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Arch-Bishop of <hi>CARTHAGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Translated into English.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:152926:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152926:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>VAin Pomp and Luxury has so far prevailed with those that wou'd be called the fair Sex, that, it seems, it were ill man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to question the lawfulness there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. An universal corruption and diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of manners, in many of them, is come to that pitch, that they seem, almost, past reclaiming. Lewdness and Debaucherie is so ordinary a sport amongst many, not only of the inferior sort of women; but also among some (if I may not say many) of the first rank and quality; that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb facs="tcp:152926:3"/>modesty, so especially recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the femal Sex, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgotten, but even contemned and trodden under foot. St. <hi>Paul</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exhorts, but also seems to command women <hi>to adorn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in modest Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel with shamefaced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and sobriety;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim. c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 9.10.</note>
               <hi>not with broidered hair or gold or pearls or costly aray; but (which becometh women professing God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness with good works.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> to the same effect. <hi>Whose adorning</hi> (says he) <hi>let it not be that outward of plaiting the hair and of wearing of gold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet. c.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 3.4.</note>
               <hi>or of putting on of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, but let it be the hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet Spirit, which is, in the sight of God, of great price.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152926:3"/>And yet no Age of Paganism cou'd ever paralel the Pomp and Luxuy of women pretending to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess Christianity; whilst, so many thousands of the living members of Jesus Christ, I mean the poor, are exposed to the injury of hunger and cold, with, scarce, so many rags as will cover their nakedness, and can hardly extort, with a great deal of importunity, one single farthing, from some of those Ladies, who have, God knows, how many pounds worth of Ribands, of Patches, of Gold and Silver Lace, and other superfluous Vanities to deck their heads and heels.</p>
            <p>It was this dolefull consideration, and a Zeal of those precious Souls captivated by the Devil, that moved me to translate this small Treatise of the Holy Martyr St. <hi>Cyprian;</hi> in hopes that some of those Ladies,
<pb facs="tcp:152926:4"/>who will not scruple to cast away four or five hours a day upon a Comedy wou'd bestow, at least, an hour or two on the reading of this, to see how different a sense this great man had of the Pomp and Luxury, so common now a days, from some mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Pastors, and blind pretended Spiritual Guides, who criminally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the word of God, with false glosses and interpretations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they not only countenance, but also seem to abet these corruptions: as if such plain text of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture needed any other comment, than the bare reading. Not that I dare hope to be able to reclaim many (for alas! such is the corruption of our Age, that few will give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the time to read it, much less, take it to heart) but that, since we are accustomed to pay a great deal of veneration to antiquity, and that the words of men eminent for piety and
<pb facs="tcp:152926:4"/>learning, especially such as flourished in the primitive Church and purest times of Christianity, are of great weight; some vertuous Ladies and Gentlewoman, considering seriously in what abomination this holy and learned Martyr held this Pagan Pomp, so much improved, in our days, by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian women, who, notwithstanding, solemnly renounced it in their Baptism, wou'd reform their Childrens Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners after this original; which may be easily done, by moderating the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of their dresses, by retrenching the extravagance of their pleasures, and diversions, especially that of the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atre, where Modesty and shamefaced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is easily shipwracked, and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty and barefaced impudence soon learned; but more particularly, by imploying some part of that time which is thrown away upon diversion, in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tising some works of Piety and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And since I come to talk of the
<pb facs="tcp:152926:5"/>Theatre; I hope the devout Reader won't be sorry I make this digression, to give him St. <hi>John Chrisostome</hi> that learned and vertuous Bishop of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> his sence of it. This great Man having lived a great while in two Imperial Cities, <hi>viz. Antioch</hi> and <hi>Constantinople,</hi> had often occasion to Preach against the disorders of the Theatre. <hi>The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy,</hi> says he, <hi>is the School of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, the Accademy of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence, the chair of pestilence. There you shall see lewd Women representing Adulteries and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Blasphemies. When you come from the Theatre, with what face can you look upon your Wife, your Children, your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, your Friends?</hi> And again he confutes the silly pretences and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish causes of those that goes there. These are his Words, <hi>What harm is it, say you, to go to the Comedy?
<pb facs="tcp:152926:5"/>does that deserve a separation from the Communion?</hi> (for it seems he used to Excommunicate such as went.) <hi>And I ask you, can there be a greater crime than to come impudently to the Holy Table, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being polluted with Adultery? Yes it's a kind of Adultery to go to the Comedy; and if you do not believe me, give ear to the Words of him who is to Judge our lives.</hi> Jesus <hi>Christ says unto us, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever looketh on a Woman to lust after her, hath committed Adultery with her already in his Heart: What may be said then of those who go on purpose to these places, where they spend the day in looking upon Women who have not the best Reputation in the World? With what Face will they maintain that they have not looked upon them with Lustful Eyes? Since there is nothing to
<pb facs="tcp:152926:6"/>be heard, but lascivous words; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be seen, but immodest actions: There you shall hear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Songs, there you are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with consorts of Musick, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to excite the most shameful Passions; there you shall see Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men trim'd with false features and colours, decked and arrayed for to inspire Love. There the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is in a confusion, and a certain sloath, which pushes them forward to the Lewdness, which this fatal train inspires them with. The Musical Instruments, the consorts and the Airs, are not less dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous;</hi> they do unhappily <hi>flatter and soften the Heart, and prepare it to run into the Net which is spread by these unfortunate and depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Women. For, if in the Church where Psalms are Sung, where the Scripture is expounded, where we have continually the fear of God
<pb facs="tcp:152926:6"/>before our Eyes, and stand with an awful respect: if, I say, even in this venerable place, Lust creeps in, how shall those, who are daily at the Play, who neither sees nor hears but what is prophane and dangerous, who are filled with unclean thoughts, whose Eyes and Ears are continually attacked, be able to resist the motions of Lust? or if that be impossible, how will they excuse themselves from the crime of Adultery? And if they are Adulterers how can they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to enter into the Church and partake of the Sacred Table, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less they Repent.</hi> Thus far St. <hi>Chrisostome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Author of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise I need not say any more of him, his Learned and Pious works suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently declare his Character to the World. This only I will say, that
<pb facs="tcp:152926:7"/>what he writ or Preached, the same he confirmed by his works in his Life, and at his death sealed it with his Blood. Touching the translation, which is my own Part, I am not ashamed to own that it lost a great deal of it's Lustre and Beauty in the change. However, if it please Almighty God to give it his Blessing, I hope it will be of some profit to the Reader, if so I have my end.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152926:7"/>
            <head>The Book of the Holy Martyr St. CYPRIAN Arch-Bishop of <hi>Carthage;</hi> of the Dicipline and Habit of Virgins.</head>
            <p>DIscipline the guardian of Hope, the keeper of Faith, the Guide in the way of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Fewel and Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a good Inclination, the Mistress of Virtue, causeth one to abide constant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Christ, to live in God, and to arive happily at the Heavenly promises, and Divine rewards. To follow this is Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; but to contemn and neglect it, is Mortal. The Holy Ghost speaks in the Psalms, <hi>Hold fast the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline lest perhaps the Lord should be angry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 2.</note>
               <hi>and ye perish from the right way, when his anger will be suddenly kindled against you.</hi> And again, <hi>God saith to the Sinner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 49.</note>
               <hi>why dost thon declare my Righteousness
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152926:8"/>and takest my Covenant by thy Mouth? Since thou hatest Discipline, and rejectest my words.</hi> And again we read, <hi>He that casts off Discipline,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sap. 3.</note>
               <hi>is unhappy.</hi> And from <hi>Solomon</hi> we receive the Commands of Wisdom advising, <hi>My Son do not neglect the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline of the Lord, neither be weary of his correction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3.</note>
               <hi>for whom the Lord loveth, he correct<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th.</hi> If then God loves whom he corrects, and corrects him that he may mend; the Brethren Likewise, especially the Priests do not hate but love those whom they correct, to the end they may amend; since God, by his Prophet <hi>Jeremias,</hi> has foretold it, and our days have declared it. <hi>I will give you Pastors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to mine heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 3.</note>
               <hi>which shall feed you with Chastening.</hi> Seeing then, that in the Holy Scriptures both old and new; Discipline is always com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; and that the Foundation of Religion and Faith proceeds from fear and observance; what should we more earnestly desire? what more willingly embrace? That, having taken a deep root
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152926:8"/>and solidly fixed our habitation upon that firm rock, we may stand unshaken against the Storms and Tempests of this World; that by those divine precepts we may attain to the gifts of Christ: considering likewise and understanding, that our Members being the Temples of God, purified and cleansed from all the dregs of the old Contagion, by the sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Sacred ablution, it is not lawfull either to Defile, or Polute them, seeing, he that defiles shall be defiled. We are the Tillers and Rulers of those Temples, let us therefore serve him, to whom we belong. St. <hi>Paul</hi> says, <hi>you do not belong to your selves, for ye are bought at a great Price, Glorifie and carry God in your Bodys;</hi> let us glory, and carry God in a pure and unspotted body; and we who are redeemed by the blood of our Lord Jesus Christ, let us obey with all submission the Commands, of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and let us endeavor, that no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure nor Prophane thing be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Temple of God, lest he being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, shou'd forsake the seat where he dwels. These are the Words of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152926:9"/>Lord both saving and teaching, heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and admonishing; <hi>Behold thou art made whole, Sin no more, lest a worse thing come unto thee.</hi> He prescribes him the Manner of living he gives him the Law of Innocence after he had given him Health. Neither does he suffer him to give the reins to his Passions, but threatens him with more grievous evils than those whereof he was cured: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is a lesser offence to have Sinned before he had known the Discipline of the Lord, which once known is almost unpardonable if Infringed. Let Men and Women, Boys and Maids, let every Sex and age look to this, and see that, for the Religion and Faith which they ow to Almighty God, that pure and Holy thing which they have received from his bounty, be not slightly look'd after, since itis written: <hi>He that Perservers unto the end shall be saved.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now my discourse is unto you ô Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, of whom I have so much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter care, by how much your Glory is the more sublime. (Virginity) is that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152926:9"/>Flower of the Ecclesiastical Blossom, the glory and Ornament of Spiritual grace, a sweet Inclination, an intire and sollid work, the Master-piece of praise and honor, the Image of God, answering to the Lords Holyness, the most Illustrious portion of the flock of Christ. The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fecundity of our Mother the Church, by these and in these doth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly Flourish: And by how much this spreading Virginity adds to its Number, so much it increases the Joy of it's Mother. To these we speak, these we exhort by Love rather than by power: not that, as being highest and lowest, but Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of our own meanness, we do assume any Liberty of Censuring; but rather out of our tenderness for them, we much more fear the assaults of the Devil. Neither is this a needless caution, or an empty fear, which takes care of the way of Salvation, which preserves the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some precepts of the Lord, that those, who Consecrated themselves to Christ, and by renouncing Carnal Concupis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, have intirely devoted their Souls and Bodys to God, should finish that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152926:10"/>work which is destined to a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; nor be Sollicitous to adorn, or please any, but their own Lord, from whom they expect the Reward of their Virginity, since he himself says: <hi>All can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive this saying, save they to whom it is given. For their are some Eunuchs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19</note>
               <hi>which were so burn from their Mothers womb, and there are some, who were made Eunuchs of Men; and there be some Eunuchs which have made themselves Evnuchs for the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> So likewise, by this voice of the Angel, the gift of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence is declared, Virginity is Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>These are they which were not defiled with Women,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 14.</note>
               <hi>for they are Virgins, these are they which follow the Lamb whither soever he goeth.</hi> Neither doth God promise the grace of Continence to Men only, and forget the Women, but because the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is a portion of the man, and was taken from him and formed, God speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, commonly in all the Scriptures, to him that was first formed, because they are both in one flesh, and by the Man is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152926:10"/>signified likewise the Woman. But if Continence doth follow Christ, and Virginity be designed for the Kingdom of God, what have they (Virgins) to do with Worldly deckings and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with which whilst they covet to please men, they offend God, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting that it is written <hi>they who please men are Confounded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psa. 51.</note>
               <hi>for God maketh no account of them.</hi> and that St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath likewise after a glorious and Sublime manner preached. <hi>If I yet pleased men, I shou'd not be the Servant of Christ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 1.</note> Now continency and Chastity does not consist in the integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Flesh alone, but also in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty and Simplicity of the Exterior or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, that according to St. <hi>Paul, the Woman that is not Married, may be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both in Body and in Spirit.</hi> The same Apostle teacheth saying; <hi>He that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married careth for the things that belong to the Lord, how he may please the Lord, but he that is Married, careth for the the things that are of the World, how he may please his Wife. So likewise, the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152926:11"/>and the Ʋnmarried Woman careth for the things of the Lord, that she may be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both in Body and Spirit.</hi> A Virgin ought not only to be so, but also to be understood, and believed to be such: to the end that when she is seen no body may doubt her being a Virgin. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection shoud extend it self equally to all: nor shou'd the Ornaments of her Body blast the fame of her Mind. Why shou'd she appear decked or adorn'd, as if she had a Husband, or sought one? If she be a Virgin, let her rather fear to please, than seek to endanger her self, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed for better and more Heavenly things; Let such as have no Husbands, whom they wou'd feign to please, be pure and perfect not only in body, but in Spirit also: For it is not Lawfull for a Virgin to deck her Features, nor to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in her flesh, or it's Beauty: whereas all their endeavors shou'd be bent against the Flesh, and their most obstinate strife, in subduing and mortifyeing their Bodys. St. <hi>Paul</hi> with a lofty Voice cries out,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note>
               <hi>God forbid that I shou'd Glory, save in the Cross of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152926:11"/>our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom the World is Crucified unto me, and I unto the World.</hi> And must a Virgin in the Church of Christ, glory in the shape of her Flesh, and Beauty of her Body? St. <hi>Paul</hi> adds, <hi>Those that are Christs have Crucified their Flesh with their Vices and Lusts.</hi> And must she, who professes to have renounced the Vices and Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscences of the flesh, be overtaken in those things to which she has Renounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? when you are found so, O Virgin, its easy to discover what you are; you boast of one thing and you affect another: you taint your self with Spots of carnal Concupiscence, whilst, at the same time you wou'd pass for a Candidate of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Modesty. Cry says the Lord to <hi>Esaias, all Flesh is Grass, and all the goodliness thereof is as the Flower of the Field: The Grass withereth, and the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Fadeth, but the Word of the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth for ever.</hi> It becometh no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, much less a Virgin, to value her self upon any Honor or Glory of her Flesh, but to thirst after the Word of God, and embrace the things that will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152926:12"/>endure for ever. Or if she must Glory in the Flesh, then Indeed she may, when she is Tormented for owning her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, when she discovers more forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, tho' a Woman, than the men who torture her, when she suffers Fire, or the Cross, or the Sword, or the Beasts, that she may be Crowned. these are the most precious Pearls of the Flesh, these the most Glorious ornaments of the Body. But there are some rich Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who abounding with a plentifull Fortune, love their Riches, and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that it is Lawful to use their goods to their content; first let such know, that she is truly Rich, who is Rich in God: that she has true Wealth, whose Wealth is Christ: that these are the true Goods, which are Spiritual, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, Heavenly, which guides us to God, and which we enjoy, with God for ever. Moreover what ever earthly things we possess in this World, and must leave after us, are as much to be contemned as the World it self is Contemptible, whose Pomps and Allurments we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce upon our Happy journey to God.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152926:12"/>St. <hi>John</hi> stirs and exhorts us, and with a Heavenly voice conjures us, saying: <hi>Love not the World, neither the things that are in the World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joa. 2.</note>
               <hi>if any man love the World, the Love of the Fathers is not in him. For all that is in the World, the Lust of the Flesh, and the Lust of the Eyes, and the Pride of Life, is not of the Father, but is of the World: and the World passeth away, and the Lust thereof: but he that doeth the will of God, abideth for ever, even as God abideth for ever.</hi> We must then pursue the things which are Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Divine, and do all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Will of God, we must fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the footsteps of our Lord, and his Divine original, who taught us, saying I did not come down from Heaven to do my own will, but the Will of him that sent me. And if the Servant be not greater than his Master, and the Freeman oweth Obedience to him that made him free; surely, we that desire to be accounted Christians, ought in all reason to immitate that, which Christ has done. It is written, it is read, it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152926:13"/>is heard, and it is publickly declared in the Church, that, <hi>he that abideth in Christ ought himself to walk,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joa. 2.</note>
               <hi>even as he hath walked.</hi> We must tread in the same path with him, we must endeavour to follow him with a Holy emulation. Then the pursuit of truth will answer the Faith we profess, and the Reward of Faith is given to him that believes, if he acts according to his belief.</p>
            <p>Thou sayst thou art Rich: but St. <hi>Paul</hi> prevents thee in thy riches, and with a Heavenly voice prescribes, how thou art to Moderate thy Dress. Let Women, says he, <hi>adorn themselves in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest apparel with shame fac'dness and Sobriety:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note>
               <hi>not with broiderd Hair or Gold, or Pearls or Cost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Aray, but (which becometh Women professing Godliness with good Works.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> likewise is of the same Opinion, saying,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.</note>
               <hi>whose Adorning, let it not be that outward of plating the Hair, &amp; of wearing of Gold, or of putting on of Apparel: but let it be the hidden Ornament of the Heart.</hi> And
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152926:13"/>if the Apostles do admonish those Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who, on pretence of their Husbands, do excuse their gaudy Dresses, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain and Moderate themselves to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious observance of the Ecclesiastial Discipline: how much more ought a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to observe it, who can pretend to no such Allowance; nor fasten the falshood of her fault upon another, since she her self is the only person to whom it can be ascribed. You say, you are Rich, but all that is in your power, is not fit to be done; neither ought those Tedious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires which proceed from Worldly Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to extend further, than what is sutable to the Honor and Modesty of a Virgin. Since it is written all things are Lawfull unto me,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> but all things are not expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Besides, if you give any Marks of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry in your Dress, and walk remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ablely in publick, if you attract and draw the Eyes and Hearts of Young men upon you, if you Cherish the Lust of their desires, if you kindle the Flames of their Hearts, so that you make them perish, tho' you do not perish, and do
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152926:14"/>kill those you see, as it were with Sword or Poison, you cannot be excused, as if your mind were Chaste and Modest: your immodest Dress and your Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet-like Ornaments reproach you: nor can you be reckoned among the Maids and Virgins of Christ, who lives in the World so, as that you may be Lov'd.</p>
            <p>You say, you are Rich; but a Virgin ought not to boast of her Riches: since the Holy Scripture says. <hi>What did our Pride advantage us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sap. 5.</note>
               <hi>or what did the Vanity of our Riches avail us? For all hath passed way like a Shaddow.</hi> And again the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle exhorteth, saying. <hi>And they that buy as tho' they Possessed not; and they that use this World, as not abusing it, for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion of this World passeth away. Peter</hi> likewise to whom the Lord gave in charge to feed and keep his flock, upon whom he founded his Church, denies to have Silver or Gold: but affirms that he is Rich in the grace of Christ, and Wealthy in his Faith and power, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he might work many and Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miracles, and abound in Spiritual
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152926:14"/>goods for his glories, sake, this Wealth, these Riches cannot be possessed by him, who wou'd rather be Rich in this world then in Christ. You say, you are Rich and Wealthy, and think you may use these things which God was willing you shou'd possess: do so, use them, but let it be for things that tends to your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, make use of them to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, use them as the Lord hath shewed and Commanded you. Let the Poor perceive that you are Rich, let the Needy find that you have Wealth, give out your Patrimony to God upon use, feed Christ: that you may bear away the glory of your Virginity, and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily attain to the reward that attends it, have the Prayers of many. Deposite your Treasure, where no Thief can dig up, where no sly Knave can break in. Acquire Riches, but let it be in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where your Fruit will be Perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and Everlasting, secured from the danger of any Secular injury, where Rust cannot Eat it, nor Hail break it, nor the Sun burn it, nor rain spoil it. for you Sin against God, even in this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152926:15"/>very thing, if you believe, Riches were given you for any other end, than to work your Salvation. For, tho' God gave Man a Voice, he ought not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to sing Lascivious and Immodest Songs therewith; he Created Iron to Till the Earth, yet we must not commit Murder with it: nor must one Sacrifice to Idols, because God produced Incense, Wine, and Fire; neither must you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Victimes to their Altars, because your Fields abound with flocks of Cattle. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise a large Patrimony is a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if not turned to good use: as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one aboundeth in Riches, so ought he rather to redeem than increase his sins. Notable Marks in Cloaths and Ornaments, and Lascivious dresses, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come none, but Prostitute and Immodest Women, and no habit is more Precious than theirs whose Modesty is least e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem'd. So in the holy Scriptures, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord wou'd have us be taught and admonished, that whore-like, and proudly decked City, which with its Ornaments, or rather, for its Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, was to perish, is described. <hi>And
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152926:15"/>there came,</hi> says <hi>St.</hi> John, <hi>one of the Seaven Angels which had the Seven Vials,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 17.</note>
               <hi>and talked with me, saying, come hither, I will shew un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, the Judgment of the great Whore, that sitteth upon many Waters: with whom the Kings of the Earth have committed Fornication. So he carried me away in the Spirit into the Wilderness: and I saw a Woman sitting upon a Beast; and the Woman was arayed in Purple, and Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Colour, and Decked with Gold, and precious Stones, and Pearls, having a Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Cup in her hand full of Abominations, and filthiess of her Fornications.</hi> Let all Chast and Modest Women shun the Deckings of the Incestuous, let them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test the dress of Strumpets, the Marks of Bawds, and the ornaments of whores. In like manner the Prophet <hi>Esaias</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenished with the Holy Ghost crys out, and reproaches the Daughters of <hi>Sion,</hi> which were corrupted by their Gold and Silver, and Aray, and severely Chides those that abounded with Pernicious Wealth. <hi>Because,</hi> says he,
<note place="margin">Esa. 3.</note>
               <hi>the Daughters of</hi> Sion <hi>are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152926:16"/>Haughty, and walk with stretched forth Necks, and wanton Eyes, Walking and Mincing as they go, &amp; making a tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with their Feet: therefore the Lord will smite with a Scab the Crown of the Head of the Daughters of</hi> Sion, <hi>and the Lord will discover their secret parts, in that day, the Lord will take away the Bravery of their Tinkling ornaments, and their cauls, and their round Tires like the Moon, the Chains, and the Bracelets, and the Mufflers, the Bonnets, and the ornaments of the Legs, and the Head-bands, and the Tablets and the Ear-rings; the chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able suits of Apparel and the Mantles, and the Wimples, and the Crysping-pins. And it shall come to pass, that instead of a Sweet smell, there shall be a Stink; and instead of a Girdle, a Rent, and instead of well set Hair there shall be Baldness.</hi> This is what God blames, this is what he remarks: hence it is, that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces Virgins Corrupted, hence it is that he declares that they have degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the true, and divine Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Being Exalted, they fell: being Decked, they deserved Dirt and filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152926:16"/>when they put on Silks and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they cannot be cloathed with Christ, being decked with Gold, and Pearls, and Precious stones, they loose the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of their Hearts and Minds. Who wou'd not detest and abhor that which was so fatal to others? Who wou'd covet or desire, that, which was like a sword or Dart to the ruin of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? If you had seen one Drink a Cup, and Die, you wou'd soon guess his drink was Poison; if you had seen one Eat and expire, you wou'd judge that, what he eat was Mortal, that cou'd so soon kill: neither wou'd you eat or drink of that, whereof you had seen others Die. Now what weakness of Understanding, what Blindness, what Madness is it, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet that, which always has &amp; does offend? What madness is't, to think that you will not Perish by that, wherewith, you are Conscious, so many to have been Killed? For God, did not make sheep of Purple or Scarlet Colour, neither did he teach men to Die and Colour wool with the juice of herbs, or with Violet, nor has he ordained Bracelets
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152926:17"/>beset with Gold, Pearls, and precious stones orderly ranked, that you may hide the Neck which he has made, that what God had formed in man may be covered, and what the Devil had inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted may appear. Wou'd God have Wounds to be made in ears, wherewith the Innocent babes that knows no evil, are Tormented, that Precious grains may hang at those Wounded ears, grains heavy, indeed, not with their own, but with the weight of their price? All which the sinfull and Apostate Angels discovered by their arts, when tumbling into Earthly contagion, they fell from their Celestial Vigor. It was they, who taught to Paint the Eye-brows with Black, and to daub the Cheeks with counterfeit red, and to alter the Hair with adulterated Colours, in a word, to besmear all the Face and Head with the filth of their Paint.</p>
            <p>And now, indeed, for the fear and care which Faith suggests to us, for the Love and tenderness, which our Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood requires of us, I think that not onely Virgins, or Widdows, but also
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152926:17"/>Wives, and all sort of Women, are to be admonished, that they shou'd by no means suffer their form and shape, which is the work of God, to be Adulterated, either with Yellow colour, or Black dust, or Red, or any other Ointment whatsoever, which defaces the Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tural Linements and the handework of the Creator.</p>
            <p>God says;
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note>
               <hi>let us make Man after our own Image and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;</hi> and will any body be so bold as to alter and change that which he has made? they lay Violent hands upon God, when they presume to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and disfigure what he has form'd; not understanding that what ever is born is the work of God, but what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is altered is the work of the Devil. If a Skillful Limner had, drawn a Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and with exquisite Colours paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to the Lise, every Feature and Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eament in the Body, and that another, pretending more skill, wou'd lay hands upon it, in order to Mend the Work, the former doubtless wou'd think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self injured and wou'd be justly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152926:18"/>and do you think, your rash Presumption will escape unpunished, who dares lay hands on a piece drawn by the hands of the Almighty? For tho' you be not Lewd, nor Immodest in the Eyes of Men, for your Prostitute paint; you are nevertheless an adultress when you Corrupt and Violate the work of God. You think to Adorn, and set your self out, but in the mean time you inpugne the Divine work, and falsifie the truth. The words of the Apostle sufficiently instructeth in this: <hi>Purge out says</hi> He <hi>the old Leaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note>
               <hi>that ye may be a new Lump, as ye are unleavened; for even Christ our Passover is Sacrificed for us. Therefore let us keep the Feast, not with old Leaven, neither with the Leaven of Malice and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; but with the unleavened bread of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and Truth.</hi> Can sincerity and truth persist, when that that is sincere is Polluted with Adulterated Colours, and truth with Sophisticated Ointments is changed into a lye? Your Lord and Master says: you cannot make one hair in your Head White or Black: and you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152926:18"/>to convince your Masters words, and shew your one skill to be greater, wou'd with a rash and Sacrilegious contempt Colour your Hair; as a future presage of your Evil, you covet to have Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den hair, and you sin (ô wickedness) in your Head, that is to say, in the most precious part of your Body; and as it is written of the Lord: <hi>His Head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 2.</note>
               <hi>and the Hair of his head was White like Wool or Snow;</hi> you abhor that hoariness, you detest that Whiteness which is like to the Lords head. Are not you affraid, pray, when the day of Judgment comes, that your Maker will not know you, and when you come to the Promised Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards will turn you away, and shut you out, saying: this is not my work, this Image is not Mine; you have pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted your Skin with false Paste, you have altered your hair with Adulterated Colours, you have taken a false Face for your own, your Figure is corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, your Countenance altered, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not see God, since you have not the Eyes which were made by God, but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152926:19"/>which were infected by the Devil. him you have followed, the Blaseing and Painted eyes of the Serpent you have Immitated, by your enemy you have been dressed, and with him you shall burn. Are not these things, I beseech you, to be considered by the Servant, of God? Are not these hourly and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be feared? Let Married women have a care how they flatter themselves with a vain pretence of pleasing their Husbands, whom, when they produce for their excuse, they joyn in the Guilt of their Criminal condescention. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Virgins, (whose good this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course chiesly Consults,) which sets themselves out with such art, are not, in my opinion, to be reckoned among Virgins: but like Mangy Cattle, or Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by sheep ought to be driven and chas'd from the pure and Holy fold of Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; lest they shou'd infect, or pollute the rest by their Contagion, whilst they live amongst them. And since our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose is to seek what is good for chaste minds, let us shun whatever is pernicious and destructive to them. Neither can I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152926:19"/>pass those things by, which being intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by a certain negligence, do u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surp a kind of Liberty contrary to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest and sober Behaviour. Some Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins are not asham'd to be present at Weddings, and with the Lascivious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scourses Generally practised on such Occasions, to mix immodest words, to hear what is not becomming, to observe what is not lawful to be told, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at obscene words and Drunken Feasts wherewith the Flames of Lusts are kindled, and the Bride encouraged to suffer the loss of her Maiden-head, and the Bridegroom prompted to the confidence of taking it.</p>
            <p>What place is there for her at Weddings, who has not a mind to Marry? or how can they be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant or Merry, where such diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and opposite wishes and desires do meet? What is there learnt? what is there seen? how much does a Virgin fail in her purpose who, was modest when she came, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modest departing? tho' she is chaste in body and mind, yet in her Eyes, in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152926:20"/>her Ears, in her Tongue she is not.</p>
            <p>But what of those Virgins, who Promiscuously with those of the other sex go to Baths? who Prostitute their Bodies, which they had before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to Chastity and Modesty, to the Lust of Lacivious Eyes, who when they see and are seen naked by Men, do they not Administer a Temptation to wickedness? does not such objects, sollicit and Invite the beholders to corrupt and defile them? But one will say, let every one see to what Intention he comes there; for my part, I have no other but to wash and refresh my Body. That plea does not purge you; nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse the crime of your Lascivious wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonness. Such a Bath does not wash but sully you, nor does it Cleanse your Members but Defile them. you look at none Lasciviously, but you your Self are Lasciviously Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon: you do not please your eyes with any foul object, but being the object that pleases others,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152926:20"/>your Self is polluted: you make a shew of the Bath, and the place where you meet is worse than the Theatre. there all modesty is put off together with your cloaths, all modesty and shame-facedness of the Body is laid aside; Virginity it self is discover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed even to be seen and handled. Now let me see, can you be modest amongst Men when you are Clothed, you, I say, whose nakedness has incouraged them to attempt your Chastity?</p>
            <p>I'ts for this reason the Church laments her Virgins, thus she Mourns for their Infamous and detestable faults, so the Flower of Virgins fad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the honor and Modesty of Chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is cut off, all their glory and worth is profaned. Thus the devouring Enemy by his execrable arts insinuates himself: thus the Devil Creeps in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensibly: thus when Virgins go about decked and trim'd, they are no more Virgins; being corrupted with their hidden disgrace, they are Widdows before they are Wives; they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultresses, not of Husbands but of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152926:21"/>Christ; and according to the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the reward which Virgins are to expect, so much shall they suffer pains for the loss of their Virginity.</p>
            <p>Hear me therefore as a Father, o Virgins; hear me, I beseech you, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structing and advising you, hear me for your own good and profit: be ye such as God your Artificer has made you: Be ye such as the Hands of your Heavenly Father has ordained you. Let not the Face be tainted, let the Neck be pure, the Countenance sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere: Let not the Ears be wounded, nor the Neck or Arms tyed up with precious Chains of Pearl or stone. —Let your feet be free from Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den featers your Hair from Sophisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated Colours. Let your Eyes be worthy to look God in the Face, use Baths among Women whose conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation may render such washings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, avoid the wicked Feasts, and Lascivious Banquets of Weddings, whose very Contagion is dangerous. You that is a Virgin, you that glory in serving the Lord shou'd be above
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152926:21"/>any thoughts of Immodest Apparel, conquer your Gold, you that tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over the Flesh and the World. 'Tis not surely the property of one and the same, not to be overcome in great, and yet to succumb in mean things.
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note>
               <hi>The way is straight and narrow which leads to life;</hi> the path is high and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult which tends to glory: by this small path the Martyrs do pass, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins do go, and every one that is just do walk. Avoid the broad and spaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way: there are Poisonous plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, and mortal allurements: there the Devil flatters, that he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; pleases, that he may hurt; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, that he may Kill. The fruit of Martyrs, as the first, is an Hundred fold; yours, as the Second is Sixty. And as their thoughts is not of the World or the Flesh, nor their strife little, light or delicate: so let your courage in suffering be next them, whose reward in glory is ranked in the Second place.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:152926:22"/>
            <p> It is not easy to attain to great things, how do we sweat, how do we labour, when we mount hills, or tops of Mountains? How great then shou'd our labour be, when we ascend to Heaven? if you consider the reward that is promis'd your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour will come far short of it. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality is given to him that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severs; an eternal Life is promised, the Lord promiseth a Kingdom. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve ô Virgins that which ye began to be. Keep that which ye will be. Great is the reward which attends you, great is the price of Virtue, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great is the reward of Chastity. Wou'd you know how great are the evils Virtue wants, and the good it possesseth. <hi>I will multiply,</hi> says God to the Woman <hi>thy Sorrow, and thy Conception:</hi>
               <note place="margin">17. Gen. 3.</note>
               <hi>In sorrow thou shalt bring forth Children: and this desire shall be to thy Husband, and he shall rule over thee.</hi> Ye are free from that decree, Ye do not fear the sorrow or groans of Women Travelling in Child-birth:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152926:22"/>Ye are in no danger of that Nature, neither is a Husband your Master, but Christ your Lord and Chief is instead of a Husband, whose Lot and Fortune is common to you.</p>
            <p>This is the voice of the Lord say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>The Children of this world Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and are given in Marriage, but they which shall be accounted worthy to obtain that World and the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the Dead, neither Marry, nor are given in Marriage. neither can they die any more for they are equal unto the Angels, and are the Children of God, being the Children of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection.</hi> What we will, that ye now begin to be. Ye do already in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the glory of the Resurrection. Ye pass through the World without the Worlds infection. Whilst ye persevere in Chastity, ye are equal to the Angels of God; provided your Chastity be pure and unspoted; and that as it begun stoutly, so it may last continually, and affect no Ornaments of Jewels or Pearls but of good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Look up on God and Heaven,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152926:23"/>and do not abase those Eyes lifted up to the Consideration of Carnal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiscence or Earthly things.</p>
            <p>The first decree Commands to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ease and Multiply: the Second ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vises Continence. When the World was in the beginning empty and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled, it was necessary to Propagate and multiply Mankind that the earth might be inhabited: but now since the World is replenished, such as have the gift of continence, make themselves Eunuchs for the Kingdom of Heaven. This the Lord commandeth not, but exhorteh. Nor doth he impose a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity upon us, since he left us a free will to use it. But seeing there are a great many Mansions with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he wou'd shew us which of them are the best: Ye thirst after these best Mansions, and if you mortifie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires of the Flesh, you will get the reward of a greater grace in Heaven. Indeed as many as attained to that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Benefit of sacred Baptism, have by the grace of thar Sacrament put of the old man, and being renewed by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152926:23"/>the Holy Ghost, are cleansed from the Filth of the old contagion by a new Regeneration. But ye, who have cast off the desires of Flesh and Blood, have a greater title to the Sanctity and purity of that Regeneration, whilst ye keep the things only that are of Virtue and of the Spirit. It's the voice of the Apostle, whom the Lord calls his chosen Vessel, and whom he sent to promulgat his Heavenly commands: <hi>The first man is of the Earth, Earthy: the second is the Lord from Heaven: as is the Earthy, such are they also that are Earthy: and as is the Heavenly, such are they also that are Heavenly. and as we have born the image of the Earthy, we shall also bear the Image of the Heavenly.</hi> This Image Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity bears, so doth integrity, so doth Truth and Holyness. Such as are mindful of the Discipline of the Lord, such as joyn Religion with Justice; such as are stead-fast in Faith, humble in fear, strong in Sufferings, mild in bearing injuries, prompt in doing works of Mercy, unanimous in peace
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152926:24"/>and concord do bear this Image. All which ô good Virgins, ye ought to observe, Love and fullfil; ye who having leasure to serve God and Christ do with a greater and more excellent part go before to the Lord to whom ye are Consecrated. Ye that are El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der instruct the Younger, ye that are Younger assist the Elder, excite your equals, stir up one an other with mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Exhortations, provoke to Glory with documents of Emulation in Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Endure stoutly, go on Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, arrive Hapily. And remember, me, when your Virginity begins to be Crowned.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>